<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-06T16:35:15+00:00</updated><id>https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&amp;%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Integration of Organic Semiconductors in Nonlinear Photonics</title><link href="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2026/Organics_Photonics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Integration of Organic Semiconductors in Nonlinear Photonics"/><published>2026-01-06T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-06T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&amp;%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2026/Organics_Photonics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&amp;%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2026/Organics_Photonics/"><![CDATA[<p><em>To be updated</em></p> <h2 id="the-integration-of-organic-semiconductors-in-nonlinear-photonics">The Integration of Organic Semiconductors in Nonlinear Photonics</h2> <p>The field of integrated photonics has reached a point where the “passive” performance of platforms like Silicon Nitride ($Si_3N_4$) is excellent, but “active” nonlinear functionalities remain a challenge. While Lithium Niobate ($LiNbO_3$) is the current industry standard, it is not without significant drawbacks, leading to increased interest in evaporated organic thin films.</p> <h3 id="the-limitations-of-lithium-niobate">The Limitations of Lithium Niobate</h3> <p>Despite its dominance, $LiNbO_3$ presents several hurdles for scalable, next-generation photonics:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Fabrication Complexity:</strong> $LiNbO_3$ is notoriously difficult to etch. While Thin-Film Lithium Niobate (TFLN) has made strides, achieving smooth sidewalls to minimize scattering loss remains a high-cost, specialized process.</li> <li><strong>Photorefractive Instability:</strong> At high optical powers—common in nonlinear optics—$LiNbO_3$ suffers from the photorefractive effect, where laser-induced charge migration changes the refractive index, leading to drift and instability.</li> <li><strong>Integration Constraints:</strong> It is difficult to grow $LiNbO_3$ directly on top of processed CMOS wafers, often requiring complex wafer-bonding techniques.</li> </ul> <h3 id="distinguishing-the-mechanisms-eo-vs-nlo">Distinguishing the Mechanisms: EO vs. NLO</h3> <p>To understand the role of organics, we must distinguish between two physical mechanisms:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Electro-Optics (EO):</strong> The change in refractive index in response to a DC or low-frequency RF electric field (The Pockels Effect).</li> <li><strong>All-Optical Nonlinear Processes:</strong> The interaction of light with light via the material’s susceptibility, such as <strong>Second-Harmonic Generation (SHG)</strong>.</li> </ul> <p>While both require a non-centrosymmetric medium, all-optical processes are significantly more sensitive to the presence of metal.</p> <h3 id="the-problem-with-electrodes">The Problem with Electrodes</h3> <p>In traditional organic photonics, molecules are aligned using <strong>electric-field poling</strong>. While this works for EO modulators, it creates a major conflict for all-optical $\chi^{(2)}$ devices:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Optical Absorption:</strong> Metal electrodes used for poling must be placed very close to the optical mode to achieve high field strengths. For all-optical processes like SHG, these electrodes introduce significant plasmonic absorption and scattering losses, which can severely degrade the efficiency of the frequency conversion.</li> <li><strong>Field Uniformity:</strong> All-optical processes require phase-matching over long propagation lengths. Maintaining a perfectly uniform poled state across a long waveguide is difficult with discrete electrodes, leading to local variations in the nonlinear coefficient.</li> </ol> <h3 id="moving-beyond-poling-the-spontaneous-approach">Moving Beyond Poling: The Spontaneous Approach</h3> <p>Our recent work, <strong>“Spontaneously-Oriented Evaporated Organic Semiconductor Thin Films for Second-Order Nonlinear Photonics”</strong> (<a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsphotonics.4c01190"><em>ACS Photonics</em> 2024</a>), addresses these challenges by utilizing molecules that naturally align during vacuum deposition.</p> <p>By eliminating the need for poling, we also eliminate the need for permanent electrodes. This allows for:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Lower Loss:</strong> No metal-induced absorption near the nonlinear medium.</li> <li><strong>Simplified Fabrication:</strong> The film is “active” as soon as it is deposited, allowing for easier hybrid integration with $Si_3N_4$ waveguides.</li> </ul> <p>However, the challenge shifts from electrical engineering to <strong>molecular engineering</strong>: designing molecules that not only have high hyperpolarizability but also the specific shape and dipole moment required to sustain orientation during the growth process—a focus of our latest <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13682">preprint on arXiv</a>.</p> <h3 id="conclusion-toward-scalable-quantum-and-classic-light-sources">Conclusion: Toward Scalable Quantum and Classic Light Sources</h3> <p>By overcoming the traditional trade-offs of organic materials, spontaneously oriented films pave the way for a new class of photonic devices. From efficient on-chip frequency doubling to the generation of entangled photon pairs via spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC), these materials offer a path toward high-performance nonlinear circuits that are both CMOS-compatible and scalable. As we refine the molecular design rules for these systems, the goal is to transition from discrete components to fully integrated nonlinear systems-on-a-chip.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pierre-Luc Thériault</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="bib"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Integration of Organic Semiconductors in Nonlinear Photonics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To be completed -&amp;gt; Power, fluence, waist and other beam parameters</title><link href="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2024/beam_size_to_power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To be completed -&amp;gt; Power, fluence, waist and other beam parameters"/><published>2024-02-18T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&amp;%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2024/beam_size_to_power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pltheriault.com/#%20the%20base%20hostname%20&amp;%20protocol%20for%20your%20site/blog/2024/beam_size_to_power/"><![CDATA[<p>A brief post expliciting how power, beam diameter, pulse duration and repetition rate are related. This is available elsewhere on the web but I wanted to write a short version which I can easily find and understand. <em>To be updated</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Pierre-Luc Thériault</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="bib"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Beam diameter, power, repetition rate, pulse duration, fluence and power]]></summary></entry></feed>